<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="/dsablog/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/dsablog/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-08-13T17:09:51+03:00</updated><id>/dsablog/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Data Science Africa Blog</title><subtitle>A Blog on Data Science Africa Events</subtitle><author><name>Data Science Africa</name></author><entry><title type="html">Data driven Covid-19 solutions in Africa</title><link href="/dsablog/2021/08/12/data-driven-covid-19-solutions-in-africa.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Data driven Covid-19 solutions in Africa" /><published>2021-08-12T17:45:13+03:00</published><updated>2021-08-12T17:45:13+03:00</updated><id>/dsablog/2021/08/12/data-driven-covid-19-solutions-in-africa</id><content type="html" xml:base="/dsablog/2021/08/12/data-driven-covid-19-solutions-in-africa.html">&lt;p&gt;Data science communities across Africa have created - and are still developing - innovative uses of data and statistics to support Covid-19 response teams in mitigating the Covid-19 Pandemic. These solutions aim to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Increase the effectiveness &lt;b&gt;of emergency response&lt;/b&gt; (like monitoring the extent of the disease spread among populations);&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Improve surveillance&lt;/b&gt; (by estimating the prevalence of Covid-19 and understanding the symptoms); and &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Aid decision making&lt;/b&gt; (by investigating how different policy interventions have affected businesses, livelihoods, and economies).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;



&lt;p&gt;By reviewing the landscape of data science-enabled Covid-19 response projects in Africa, this project aims to identify policy interventions that can enable more effective data sharing in future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Where are these solutions located?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://public.tableau.com/views/DDCSC/Dashboard1?:language=en-US&amp;publish=yes&amp;:display_count=n&amp;:origin=viz_share_link&quot;&gt;https://public.tableau.com/views/DDCSC/Dashboard1?:language=en-US&amp;publish=yes&amp;:display_count=n&amp;:origin=viz_share_link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class='tableauPlaceholder' id='viz1628845703903' style='position: relative'&gt;&lt;noscript&gt;&lt;a href='#'&gt;&lt;img alt='Dashboard 1 ' src='https:&amp;#47;&amp;#47;public.tableau.com&amp;#47;static&amp;#47;images&amp;#47;DD&amp;#47;DDCSC&amp;#47;Dashboard1&amp;#47;1_rss.png' style='border: none' /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/noscript&gt;&lt;object class='tableauViz'  style='display:none;'&gt;&lt;param name='host_url' value='https%3A%2F%2Fpublic.tableau.com%2F' /&gt; &lt;param name='embed_code_version' value='3' /&gt; &lt;param name='site_root' value='' /&gt;&lt;param name='name' value='DDCSC&amp;#47;Dashboard1' /&gt;&lt;param name='tabs' value='no' /&gt;&lt;param name='toolbar' value='yes' /&gt;&lt;param name='static_image' value='https:&amp;#47;&amp;#47;public.tableau.com&amp;#47;static&amp;#47;images&amp;#47;DD&amp;#47;DDCSC&amp;#47;Dashboard1&amp;#47;1.png' /&gt; &lt;param name='animate_transition' value='yes' /&gt;&lt;param name='display_static_image' value='yes' /&gt;&lt;param name='display_spinner' value='yes' /&gt;&lt;param name='display_overlay' value='yes' /&gt;&lt;param name='display_count' value='yes' /&gt;&lt;param name='language' value='en-US' /&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/div&gt;                &lt;script type='text/javascript'&gt;                    var divElement = document.getElementById('viz1628845703903');                    var vizElement = divElement.getElementsByTagName('object')[0];                    if ( divElement.offsetWidth &gt; 800 ) { vizElement.style.width='100%';vizElement.style.height='851px';} else if ( divElement.offsetWidth &gt; 500 ) { vizElement.style.minWidth='420px';vizElement.style.maxWidth='650px';vizElement.style.width='100%';vizElement.style.minHeight='587px';vizElement.style.maxHeight='887px';vizElement.style.height=(divElement.offsetWidth*0.75)+'px';} else { vizElement.style.width='100%';vizElement.style.height='727px';}                     var scriptElement = document.createElement('script');                    scriptElement.src = 'https://public.tableau.com/javascripts/api/viz_v1.js';                    vizElement.parentNode.insertBefore(scriptElement, vizElement);                &lt;/script&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;caption text-muted&quot;&gt;Figure 1: shows No of data driven Covid-19 solutions collected by country, (which is not a representation of all country solutions due to data collection limitations)&lt;/span&gt;




&lt;p&gt;In April(2021), we set out to collect data about data driven Covid-19 solutions in Africa, with the aim of analysing various characteristics of the projects and  developing a data sharing framework for social good beyond Covid-19 in the African context. We wanted to explore the datasets and data access strategies used, the skills and expertise needed for effective collaborations, technical requirements, and barriers to effective data sharing. Our objective for this review was to learn more about the challenges and opportunities encountered on various projects. We hope to establish where projects face common challenges, where there is consensus about the need for policy intervention, and what type of policy intervention could help. &lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;To date, we have collected about 65 data driven Covid-19 solutions and initiatives in Africa from both &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/forms/d/e/1FAIpQLSdLSRSxjIVZeXqVLcWbtv1t_IqzXP6gXbhFCIfzeIulDY6DhA/viewform&quot;&gt;the survey&lt;/a&gt; and targeted online search. This write up is an overview of our findings and a summary of the ongoing and future work towards developing a data sharing framework and contributing to &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.datascienceafrica.org/dsa-visiting-fellowship/&quot;&gt;Data Science Africa’s efforts to support data policies&lt;/a&gt; in Africa.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;What do we know so far?&lt;/h3&gt;




&lt;script src=&quot;https://code.highcharts.com/highcharts.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;https://code.highcharts.com/highcharts-more.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;https://code.highcharts.com/modules/exporting.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;https://code.highcharts.com/modules/accessibility.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highcharts-figure&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div id=&quot;packedBubble&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;
Highcharts.chart('packedBubble', {
    chart: {
        type: 'packedbubble',
        height: '100%'
    },
    title: {
        text: ''
    },
    tooltip: {
        useHTML: true,
        pointFormat: '&lt;b&gt;{point.name}:&lt;/b&gt; {point.value}'
    },
                    colors: [
                    '#5D6263',
                    '#CF5C42',
                    '#00447C',
                    '#00AEEF', 
                    '#F4D5E3', 
                    '#487D7D', 
                    '#ACE8E6', 
                    '#E7E247'
                    ],
    plotOptions: {
        packedbubble: {
            minSize: '30%',
            maxSize: '120%',
            zMin: 0,
            zMax: 30,
            layoutAlgorithm: {
                splitSeries: false,
                gravitationalConstant: 0.02
            },
            dataLabels: {
                enabled: true,
                format: '{point.name}: &lt;b&gt;{point.value}&lt;/b&gt;',
                filter: {
                    property: 'y',
                    operator: '&gt;',
                    value: 5
                },
                style: {
                    color: 'black',
                    textOutline: 'none',
                    fontWeight: 'normal'
                }
            }
        }
    },
    series: [ {
        name: 'No of Solutions',
        data: [{
            name: &quot;Replicable Data Driven Solutions&quot;,
            value: 6
        },
        {
            name: &quot;Data Driven Research Papers&quot;,
            value: 9
        },
        {
            name: &quot;Other Data Driven Covid-19 Resources&lt;br&gt;(webiners, articles, AI enabled solutions etc)&quot;,
            value: 10
        },
        {
            name: &quot;Covid-19 Data Resources&quot;,
            value: 14
        }]
    }]
});

&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;caption text-muted&quot;&gt;Figure 2: shows The data driven Covid-19 solutions analysed so far cut across a variety of data types and other general initiatives as shown in the following figures.  &lt;/span&gt;





&lt;figure class=&quot;highcharts-figure&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div id=&quot;container1&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;
Highcharts.chart('container1', {
    chart: {
        type: 'bar'
    },
    title: {
        text: 'Summary of data types used (as of the data collected)'
    },
    subtitle: {
        text: ''
    },
    xAxis: {
        categories: ['Mobile Phone Data', 'Official Health Data &amp;amp; Covid Statistics', 'Social Media, Search &amp;amp; News Data', 'Satellite Imagery', 'Survey &amp;amp; Other Data', 'Financial Data', 'X-ray Imagery'],
        title: {
            text: null
        }
    },
    yAxis: {
        min: 0,
        title: {
            text: '#',
            align: 'high'
        },
        labels: {
            overflow: 'justify'
        }
    },
    tooltip: {
        valueSuffix: ''
    },
    plotOptions: {
        bar: {
            dataLabels: {
                enabled: true
            }
        }
    },
    legend: {
        layout: 'vertical',
        align: 'right',
        verticalAlign: 'top',
        x: -40,
        y: 80,
        floating: true,
        borderWidth: 1,
        backgroundColor:
            Highcharts.defaultOptions.legend.backgroundColor || '#FFFFFF',
        shadow: true
    },
    credits: {
        enabled: false
    },
    series: [{
        name: '#',
        data: [10, 6, 4, 2, 2, 1, 1]
    }]
});
&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;caption text-muted&quot;&gt;Figure 3: shows a Summary of data types used (as of the data collected)&lt;/span&gt;



&lt;p&gt;We have tried to explore the status (i.e., level of solution uptake in the real world) of the projects in our database by categorizing them as; &lt;b&gt;pilot not ready to deploy, pilot ready to deploy&lt;/b&gt; and &lt;b&gt;in use&lt;/b&gt;. This kind of analysis will help us draw some insights into solution uptake and what roles various factors like data used, nature of collaborations, stakeholders involved and more, play in solution uptake.  Extracting any patterns in projects that get used and those that stay at pilot level (or research level) can provide insights that can help inform future approaches to projects, to increase their chances of being adopted in the real world. &lt;/p&gt;



&lt;h3&gt;What’s in progress?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are currently conducting a case-by-case analysis of the Covid-19 solutions to establish the Africa situation in regards to data sharing for social good and also identify focal points for targeted engagements.  Survey responses so far have highlighted the following key areas for action:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5&gt;-&gt; Data:&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A variety of different data types can be used in Covid-19 response, and different data types will pose different analytical challenges. Data scientists are grappling with issues of accessibility and usability, with different levels of data quality or data formats, and with questions about storage and sharing formats, and replicable frameworks available to process and analyze various data types&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h5&gt;-&gt; Collaborations:&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For an application to work well once deployed, it must be designed with user needs in mind. Survey respondents have been grappling with understanding which stakeholders have what requirements, and how best to engage with different potential user groups, defining the roles that different actors play across a project’s life, uptake, and impact. &lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h5&gt;-&gt; Skills:&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Effective deployment of data science applications requires teams with diverse skillsets that can engage different stakeholders. Further work is now needed to understand what capabilities are needed in a data science team, and how to access this multidisciplinary expertise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5&gt;-&gt; Data stewardship:&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition to issues of data access, a variety of data stewardship issues must be addressed to ensure trustworthy use of data. This project will seek to understand the challenges that arise across the data pipeline from creation, ownership, accessibility, and sharing for data analysis and use. This includes consideration of topics such as privacy, security, and the cultural norms that govern these practices and come up with checklist toolkits to aid future work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5&gt;-&gt; Policy:&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Drawing from these experiences, this project will seek to establish how the challenges tie into the policy requirements of data access and use, and propose guidelines for handling requirements, barriers, opportunities, gaps, risks, and approaches to data sharing.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;What questions need to be answered?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What data access strategies have been successful during and can be adopted from the Covid-19 response? How could these be adopted in the longer-term?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What intervention processes and procedures have proved productive in forming data collaborations for Covid-19 response? How have projects brought users or other stakeholders into project development?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What issues of data governance and data stewardship were encountered during the Covid-19 response? What privacy obligations, technical requirements and social and cultural barriers affect data sharing? &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What roles do skills and expertise play in building effective data collaborations?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How can we build capabilities in the long-term?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What policy interventions would help address or lessen the impact of the current barriers to the use of data science in policy?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why are some solutions more widespread and others not?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The study of the above mentioned factors (data, collaborations, skills, stewardship and policies) plus answering these questions will help us develop an operational context that fosters data sharing, and derive guidelines on &lt;b&gt;best practices&lt;/b&gt; that can be adapted and replicated, &lt;b&gt;lessons&lt;/b&gt; from what did not work and &lt;b&gt;recommendations&lt;/b&gt; from what has worked in the Covid-19 response. We will then map out practical actions that can create data ecosystems that foster data sharing, increasing the use of data for innovation and social good. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;caption text-muted&quot;&gt;Acknowledgements for data collection go to: &lt;b&gt;Wuraola Oyewusi, Ayomide Owoyemi, Ernest Mwebaze, Jessica Oyugi, Aurelle Tchagna Kouanou, Tamaro Green, Ezekiel Adebayo Ogundepo and Vasileios Lampos.&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/span&gt;</content><author><name>Morine Amutorine &amp; Jessica Montgomery</name></author><summary type="html">Data science communities across Africa have created - and are still developing - innovative uses of data and statistics to support Covid-19 response teams in mitigating the Covid-19 Pandemic. These solutions aim to:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Data Science Africa (DSA) Uganda Network</title><link href="/dsablog/2021/06/25/data-science-africa-uganda-network.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Data Science Africa (DSA) Uganda Network" /><published>2021-06-25T17:45:13+03:00</published><updated>2021-06-25T17:45:13+03:00</updated><id>/dsablog/2021/06/25/data-science-africa-uganda-network</id><content type="html" xml:base="/dsablog/2021/06/25/data-science-africa-uganda-network.html">&lt;p&gt;Two members of the Lab are on the interim coordination team for setting up DSA Uganda network whose mission is an all-inclusive network of data scientists, enthusiasts, and organisations inspired to grow data science skills and their usage to contribute to Uganda's development aspirations, as started in the National Development Plan III (NDPIII). The network also has clear objectives and proposed activities  for details visit the  &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.datascienceafrica.org/dsaUganda/&quot;&gt;website: http://www.datascienceafrica.org/dsaUganda/&lt;/a&gt;
The network has so far organised three pre-launch events the details of follow in the next part of his annex.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h2 class=&quot;section-heading&quot;&gt;Events&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;1st DSA Uganda Pre launch  Event&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h4 class=&quot;subheading&quot;&gt;Date: April 30, 2021&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Event link: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.datascienceafrica.org/dsaUganda/events/pre-launch.html&quot;&gt;http://www.datascienceafrica.org/dsaUganda/events/pre-launch.html&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first pre launch event was organised around the following objectives:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;To bring together partners working in the data science space within the country (Academia, UN, civil society, private sector (banking, insurance, fintech, utility, social security), government [local, and central];&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;To showcase local case studies and potential of data science and increase its awareness;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;To increase interest and ownership in data science among stakeholders;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;To Communicate the agenda of the local chapter so that the people can be aware of what is available on offer and simulate discussion on the partnership going forward.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;291 individuals applied for the event, categorised in the following areas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;District distribution:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table class=&quot;table table-bordered table-striped table-hover&quot;&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Kampala&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;163&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Gomba&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Wakiso&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;25&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Luwero&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Mbarara&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;14&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Kibaale&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Tororo&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;7&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Pader&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Lira&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;7&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Abim&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Busia&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Masaka&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Jinja&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Lyantonde&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Mukono&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Moyo&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Arua&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Ntungamo&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Apac&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Adjumani&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Kyenjojo&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Kotido&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Buikwe&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Kwania&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Gulu&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Yumbe&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Mpigi&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Contributors to the first pre launch event were; &lt;b&gt;Data Science Africa Org,  National Planning Authority (NPA), Sunbird AI, Makerere AI Lab, Busitema AI Lab, AirQo, Umeme, MTN Uganda and Stanbic Bank.&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;h3&gt;2nd  DSA Uganda Pre launch  Event&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Date: May 28, 2021&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Event link: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.datascienceafrica.org/dsaUganda/events/pre-launch-2.html&quot;&gt;http://www.datascienceafrica.org/dsaUganda/events/pre-launch-2.html&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second pre launch event was themed around opportunities in, for and around data science in Uganda and attracted presentations from government institutions, policy makers, industry experts, research institutes, academic institutions, entrepreneurs, among others giving  examples of opportunities for and around data science in Uganda. 346 individuals applied for the event, with applicants from 5 new districts of &lt;b&gt;Mbale, Kayunga, Hoima, Soroti and Kween.&lt;/b&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Contributors to the second pre launch event were; &lt;b&gt;Ministry of ICT Uganda, NITAU, ClinicPesa, Pollicy, Innovation Village Uganda, FINCA Bank and Data Science Africa Network.&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;3rd  DSA Uganda Pre launch  Event&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Date: June 25, 2021&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Event link: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.datascienceafrica.org/dsaUganda/events/pre-launch-3.html&quot;&gt;http://www.datascienceafrica.org/dsaUganda/events/pre-launch-3.html&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The third pre launch event was themed around Showcasing data science research and projects in Universities. The event was centered around student research and this is basically to encourage and foster the growth of AI research at universities through networkings and collaborations, mentorships and supervisions from experts in industry or even other universities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Contributors to the second pre launch event were from six Universities, 5 Ugandan including;&lt;b&gt; Makerere University; Uganda Technical And Management University; Gulu University; Mbarara University of Science and Technology; and Busitema University&lt;/b&gt;, then &lt;b&gt;Rhodas University&lt;/b&gt; in South Africa. The presenters included two University lecturers and six students.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;To date, data science Africa Uganda chapter has attracted participation from 388 students, researchers and professionals that make up the local community of the Uganda Network.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The map in Figure 2, shows participants residential/work distributions among the 15 sub regions of Uganda. Because of the 42 day lock down the launch that was due in July is now postponed to a later month, but pre-launch events organised by the regions will start this month, with the Northern region ( 4 subregions of West Nile, Achioli, Lango and Karamoja) organising this month.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;h2 class=&quot;section-heading&quot;&gt;Statistics from 1st and 2nd Pre-Launch Events&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;script src=&quot;https://code.highcharts.com/highcharts.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;https://code.highcharts.com/modules/exporting.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;https://code.highcharts.com/modules/export-data.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;https://code.highcharts.com/modules/accessibility.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highcharts-figure&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div id=&quot;container&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;caption text-muted&quot;&gt;Figure 1: Participant distribution from 1st and 2nd Pre-Launch Event &lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;script&gt;
Highcharts.chart('container', {
    chart: {
        type: 'bar'
    },
    title: {
        text: 'Participant Distribution by Stakeholder'
    },
    xAxis: {
        categories: ['Academia', 'Private Sector', 'Others', 'NGO', 'Goverment-Central', 'UN', 'Goverment-Local'],
        title: {
            text: 'Institutions'
        }
    },
    yAxis: {
        min: 0,
        title: {
            text: 'Participants',
            align: 'high'
        },
        labels: {
            overflow: 'justify'
        }
    },
    plotOptions: {
        bar: {
            dataLabels: {
                enabled: true
            }
        }
    },
    legend: {
        layout: 'vertical',
        align: 'right',
        verticalAlign: 'top',
        x: -40,
        y: 80,
        floating: true,
        borderWidth: 1,
        backgroundColor:
            Highcharts.defaultOptions.legend.backgroundColor || '#FFFFFF',
        shadow: true
    },
    credits: {
        enabled: false
    },
    series: [{
        name: '#Participants',
        data: [140, 80, 30, 30, 21, 16, 14]
    }, ]
});
&lt;/script&gt;




&lt;img class=&quot;img-fluid&quot; src=&quot;/dsablog/img/posts/Participant-distribution-by-stakeholder.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Demo Image&quot;&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;caption text-muted&quot;&gt;Figure 2: Map showing the distribution of participants in the three DSA Uganda pre-launch events&lt;/span&gt;



&lt;p&gt;List of 28 Universities and Higher Institutions have so far participated  in DSA Uganda Network events.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table class=&quot;table table-bordered table-striped table-hover&quot;&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Africa Leadership Institute, Uganda&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Aptech Computer Education &lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Busitema University&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Cavendish University&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Clarke International University&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;DAYSTAR University&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Ernest Cook Ultrasound Research and Education Institute&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Gulu University&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;ISBAT University&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Islamic University In Uganda &lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Jomo Kenyatta University of Technology&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Kampala International University&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Kyambogo University&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Lira University&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Makerere University&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Makerere University of Business School&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Mbarara University of Science and Technology&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Muni University&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Namasuba college of commerce &lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Nexus International University&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Nkumba university&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Strathmore university&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Uganda Christian University&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Uganda Institute of ICT (UICT)&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Uganda Martyrs University&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Uganda Technology and Management University&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;University of Nairobi&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Victoria University&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Participants have so far been drawn from 13 government Ministries/ Departments/Agencies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table class=&quot;table table-bordered table-striped table-hover&quot;&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Ministry of Health&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;National Water and Sewerage Corporation&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Uganda National Meteorological Authority&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;National Social Security Fund&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Ministry of ICT &amp; NG&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;National Planning Authority&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;National IT Authority Uganda&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Uganda Electricity Distribution Company Limited&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Uganda Broadcasting Corporation&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Mulago National Referral Hospital&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Ministry of Public Service&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Uganda Registration Services Bureau&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Uganda Investment Authority&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;</content><author><name>Data Science Africa</name></author><summary type="html">Two members of the Lab are on the interim coordination team for setting up DSA Uganda network whose mission is an all-inclusive network of data scientists, enthusiasts, and organisations inspired to grow data science skills and their usage to contribute to Uganda's development aspirations, as started in the National Development Plan III (NDPIII). The network also has clear objectives and proposed activities for details visit the website: http://www.datascienceafrica.org/dsaUganda/ The network has so far organised three pre-launch events the details of follow in the next part of his annex.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Data Science Africa support</title><link href="/dsablog/2020/07/24/data-science-africa-support.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Data Science Africa support" /><published>2020-07-24T17:45:13+03:00</published><updated>2020-07-24T17:45:13+03:00</updated><id>/dsablog/2020/07/24/data-science-africa-support</id><content type="html" xml:base="/dsablog/2020/07/24/data-science-africa-support.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;text-secondary&quot;&gt;At a glance:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;
    396 individuals applied for the eventThe virtual event hosted by Makerere University attracted participation from East Africa and beyond as the sessions could be accessed virtually. &lt;span class=&quot;text-secondary&quot;&gt;Attendance by affiliation:&lt;/span&gt; academia, private sector, research institutions, government, and industry. &lt;span class=&quot;text-secondary&quot;&gt;Key DSA counterpart (s)&lt;/span&gt; Data Science Africa Network, Makerere University, Pulse Lab Kampala, Makerere AI Research Lab, AirQo , Facebook, Google. &lt;span class=&quot;text-secondary&quot;&gt;Sponsors:&lt;/span&gt; Facebook and ARM&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 class=&quot;section-heading&quot;&gt;Summer School on Machine Learning and Data Science &lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The summer school on machine learning and data science targeted graduate students, researchers and professionals working with large quantities of data.  The sessions were spread across 4 days, 24&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt;, 25&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt;, 28&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt; and 29&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt; of July 2020. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The following 19 topics were covered;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table class=&quot;table table-bordered table-striped table-hover&quot;&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Introduction to Python &amp;amp; Jupyter Environment&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Classification and Regression&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Visualizing high dimensional data with PCA and tSNE&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Data Visualization : Communicating Insights and Results Effectively&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Anomaly Detection&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;MD4SG: Mechanism Design for Social Good&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Introduction to Process Mining: Data Science in Action&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Global Challenges in Economics and Computation&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Introduction to Spatial Data Analysis&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Deep Learning Practicals&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Data for Good&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Computer Vision&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Natural Language Processing&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Social Media Data Analysis&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Trans-African HydroMeteorological Observatory (TAHMO)&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Machine Learning Systems, Streaming Data&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Exploring R for Spatial Analytic&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Ethics in ML for Health&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Data Engineering in Integrity/Security&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;


&lt;h2 class=&quot;section-heading&quot;&gt;Workshop (30th July and 1st August)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The workshops were organized around presentations of how application of data science methods are applied to problems relevant to Africa and last year in particular saw more presentations around agricultural solutions among other topics in the areas including: healthcare, social media, geospatial modelling, economic monitoring, resume writing, Internet Of Things and data science for the Sustainable Development Goals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A panel discussion on Data Science Africa Uganda Network  was conducted. The panel discussion consisted of a dialogue on the benefits of growing local data science chapters that would duplicate the activities of data science to students, researchers and professionals at a local level (by region and districts) in Uganda. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 class=&quot;section-heading&quot;&gt;Countries that Participated&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;table class=&quot;table table-bordered table-striped table-hover&quot;&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;td rowspan=&quot;6&quot; style=&quot;width: 20%;&quot;&gt;Africa (23 Countries)&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Benin&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Botswana&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Burkina Faso&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Burundi&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Cameroon&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Congo&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Côte d'Ivoire&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Egypt&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Ethiopia&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Ghana&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Kenya&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Libya&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Malawi&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Morocco&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Nigeria&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Rwanda&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;South Africa&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Sudan&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Tanzania&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Togo&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Zambia&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Zimbabwe&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Uganda&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;td rowspan=&quot;4&quot;&gt;Outside of Africa (13 countries)&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Australia&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Bangladesh&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Czech Republic&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;France&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;India&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Ireland&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Kuwait&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Poland&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Russia&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Spain&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Sweden&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;United Kingdom&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;United States&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;h2 class=&quot;section-heading&quot;&gt;Achievements of DSA since 2015&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of the achievements that DSA  has attained with the Labs collaboration since 2015 include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Organised week long events in six African countries including Kenya, Uganda, Tanzania, Ghana, Nigeria and Ethiopia. End of this year these countries will have increased to eight with South Africa and Senegal.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;DSA has given out research grants each worth 10,000USD to 10 research teams across Africa, after a competitive application process with more 121 applications&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Attracted high level data science expertise from academia, private sector, civil society, governments, UN and NGO to instruct in summer schools and showcase their work in workshops - at their own cost travel and accommodation.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;DSA has received participation from 28 African countries, these countries are shared in Figure 1. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;img class=&quot;img-fluid&quot; src=&quot;/dsablog/img/posts/participating-28-african-countries.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Demo Image&quot;&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;caption text-muted&quot;&gt;Figure 1:  Map of Africa showing countries that have citizens that have participated or benefited from DSA since 2015.&lt;/span&gt;</content><author><name>Data Science Africa</name></author><summary type="html">At a glance: 396 individuals applied for the eventThe virtual event hosted by Makerere University attracted participation from East Africa and beyond as the sessions could be accessed virtually. Attendance by affiliation: academia, private sector, research institutions, government, and industry. Key DSA counterpart (s) Data Science Africa Network, Makerere University, Pulse Lab Kampala, Makerere AI Research Lab, AirQo , Facebook, Google. Sponsors: Facebook and ARM</summary></entry></feed>