<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://www.datascienceafrica.org/dsablog/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://www.datascienceafrica.org/dsablog/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2024-01-19T19:38:22+03:00</updated><id>http://www.datascienceafrica.org/dsablog/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Data Science Africa Blog</title><subtitle>Home for everything DSA</subtitle><author><name>Data Science Africa</name></author><entry><title type="html">Data Science Africa joins international partners to launch the International Computation and AI Network (ICAIN)</title><link href="http://www.datascienceafrica.org/dsablog/2024/01/19/data-science-africa-joins-international-partners-to-launch-icain.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Data Science Africa joins international partners to launch the International Computation and AI Network (ICAIN)" /><published>2024-01-19T17:45:13+03:00</published><updated>2024-01-19T17:45:13+03:00</updated><id>http://www.datascienceafrica.org/dsablog/2024/01/19/data-science-africa-joins-international-partners-to-launch-icain</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://www.datascienceafrica.org/dsablog/2024/01/19/data-science-africa-joins-international-partners-to-launch-icain.html">&lt;p&gt;Data Science Africa in collaboration with The Swiss Federal Department of Foreign Affairs (FDFA), ETH Zurich, EPFL, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://ellis.eu/&quot;&gt;European Laboratory for Learning and Intelligent Systems (ELLIS)&lt;/a&gt;, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cscs.ch/&quot;&gt;Swiss National Computing Centre (CSCS)&lt;/a&gt;, and the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lumi-supercomputer.eu/lumi-consortium/&quot;&gt;LUMI consortium&lt;/a&gt; launched the &lt;b&gt;International Computation and AI Network (ICAIN)&lt;/b&gt; at the World Economic Forum (WEF) 2024 in Davos. Its mission is to develop AI technologies that benefit society as a whole, as well as being accessible to all and sustainable, thereby helping to reduce global inequality.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Artificial intelligence (AI) is one of the most critical technologies of our time. It is set to radically transform our society, economy and politics, and also has the potential to combat global challenges such as climate change, pandemics and income inequality. Many countries are therefore trying to expand their AI capabilities and invest in the necessary infrastructure. But many potential players, especially in the Southern Hemisphere, have no access to the relevant technologies due to the high cost and shortage of key components.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Sharing DSA’s unique perspective&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The founders of the &lt;b&gt;International Computation and AI Network&lt;/b&gt; want to open up access to supercomputing, data and software infrastructures, as well as AI know-how, to a wider community. The aim is to facilitate international research projects that benefit society as a whole and promote the United Nations Sustainability Development Goals (SDGs). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;DSA will lead one of the pilot use cases of the network aimed at using artificial intelligence to make agriculture more resilient to the negative effects of climate change. This is an area DSA members have shown great expertise.  “For us, the cooperation with ICAIN is interesting because it opens up new opportunities for our members in the implementation of AI projects within the African context. We also want to share the unique expertise of DSA members for the benefit of others within the network,” says Professor Ciira Maina, Board Chair of Data Science Africa.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;text-align:center&quot;&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;/dsablog/img/icain-1.jpg&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; height= &quot;100%&quot; style=&quot;padding:6px&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Ciira Maina</name></author><summary type="html">Data Science Africa in collaboration with The Swiss Federal Department of Foreign Affairs (FDFA), ETH Zurich, EPFL, the European Laboratory for Learning and Intelligent Systems (ELLIS), the Swiss National Computing Centre (CSCS), and the LUMI consortium launched the International Computation and AI Network (ICAIN) at the World Economic Forum (WEF) 2024 in Davos. Its mission is to develop AI technologies that benefit society as a whole, as well as being accessible to all and sustainable, thereby helping to reduce global inequality.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Synergizing Data Science and Space Technology for Addressing Key African Agricultural Bottleneck</title><link href="http://www.datascienceafrica.org/dsablog/2023/10/26/synergizing-data-science.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Synergizing Data Science and Space Technology for Addressing Key African Agricultural Bottleneck" /><published>2023-10-26T18:04:13+03:00</published><updated>2023-10-26T18:04:13+03:00</updated><id>http://www.datascienceafrica.org/dsablog/2023/10/26/synergizing-data-science</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://www.datascienceafrica.org/dsablog/2023/10/26/synergizing-data-science.html">&lt;b&gt;Why and How Satellite based Yield Prediction ?&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Smallholder farming is a predominant global agricultural system. In the developing world, it takes the lion share, for instance, in Ethiopia, it produced about 95% of 
 main crops and cash crops. Despite its dominance, this farming practice, largely, is characterized by low crop productivity and absence of, and if there is any, the use of 
 old-age unproductive technologies. Consequently, millions of societies around the globe are threatened by food insecurity. Countries like Ethiopia, for instance, imported 
 30% - 50% of their wheat demand annually. 
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
With the fast advancement of space technologies, remote sensing (RS)-based prediction methods are preferred over traditional tiresome and costly ground surveys. 
 In harnessing the potential of remote sensing technologies, optical and radar sensors, in their order, probably are the two widely explored technologies. Existing 
 prediction methods, which often operate at national and regional scales, exploit the potential of the well-established coarse spatial and temporal resolution sensors. 
 Nonetheless, the resolution of these sensors has limited their application for field-scale prediction in smallholder systems. Data mining methods are also the 
 key components of prediction methods. Despite statistical methods are widely being exploited the new era methods: machine learning and deep learning present superior potential.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
 In this regard, this study was motivated to address some of challenges in yield prediction via setting threefold objective. First, the study aimed to evaluate the potential of selected vegetation indices derived from Sentinel-2 data that were representative of an optical sensor as wheat yield predictors. Second, it was set to evaluate the potential of selected SAR indices derived from Sentinel-1 data as wheat yield predictors. Third, we aimed to apply fast, reproducible, and open-source statistical, machine learning, and deep learning algorithms for wheat yield prediction.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
 &lt;b&gt;Key Findings&lt;/b&gt; 
 &lt;br&gt;
 &lt;br&gt;
This study aimed to develop a method for remote sensing-based wheat yield prediction. The study obtained predictors from vegetation indices derived from high-resolution optical and SAR sensors. Eight vegetation indices were computed from Sentinel-2 sensor, and five SAR indices were calculated from the Sentinel-1 sensor. In light of tapping the diverse potential, data mining methods, which are grouped under three broad categories: statistical, machine learning, and deep learning, were applied. 
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
The combined-date SAR indices, such as SAR Normalized Difference (SND) and SAR Simple Ratio (SSR) showed relatively improved performance over single date SAR indices. Indices such as SND and SSR achieved values of 1.32 ton/ha and 1.20 ton/ha, and values of 1.24 ton/ha and 1.22 ton/ha for LOORMSE (leave-one-out RMSE) and RMSE, respectively. It is intuitive to expect combined-date indices integrating wider phenological information to outperform narrow ones, single date.
 &lt;br&gt;
 &lt;br&gt;
 The most salient result of the current study is the successful application of an Automated Machine Learning platform, AutoML. The AutoML easily offers the 10 most powerful predictors (see figure 1) of
the total 48 predictors considered. The 10 influential predictors are:
 &lt;br&gt;
 &lt;br&gt;
1. lai1020ha (leaf area index dated on October 20 per hectare)
 &lt;br&gt;
2. ndwi1010ha (normalized difference water index dated on October 10 per hectare)
 &lt;br&gt;
3. lai1010ha (leaf area index dated on October 10 per hectare)
 &lt;br&gt;
4. ndwi1015ha (normalized difference water index dated on October 15 per hectare)
 &lt;br&gt;
5. mcari1010ha (modified chlorophyll absorption ratio Index dated on October 10 per hectare)
 &lt;br&gt;
6. fapar1010ha (fraction of absorbed photosynthetically active radiation index dated on October 10 per hectare)
 &lt;br&gt;
7. ndwi1020ha (normalized difference water index dated on October 20 per hectare)
 &lt;br&gt;
8. vh1015ha (single date synthetic aperture radar cross polarized index dated on October 15 per hectare)
 &lt;br&gt;
9. ndi451010ha (normalized difference index using band 4 and 5 dated on October 10 per hectare),
 &lt;br&gt;
10. fapar1005ha (fraction of absorbed photosynthetically active radiation index dated on October 05 per hectare)
 &lt;br&gt;
 &lt;br&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;text-align:center&quot;&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;/dsablog/img/bar.png&quot; width=&quot;75% height= &quot;100%&quot; center&quot; style=&quot;padding:6px&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
 &lt;br&gt;
&lt;em&gt;
 Figure 1. A plot showing the top ten most influential variables using the GLM model.
Discriminating the ten parameters, a stand-alone algorithm: the GLM model, which happens the best of all the tested algorithms, revealed an RMSE of 0.84–0.98 ton/ha for the mean population at a 99% confidence interval (CI) on the test dataset, while the performance on the training dataset was 0.84–0.88 ton/ha. Of all the predictors evaluated, leaf area index calculated at the post-grain-filling stage is the most influential one (see figure 1 above).
 &lt;/em&gt;
 &lt;br&gt;
 &lt;br&gt;
 Validation of results also implemented to come up with conclusive outputs (see figure 2). On the test dataset, six scatter plots for six GLM models using different seeds were computed. Accordingly, the correlation coefficient (r) between the estimated and measured yield ranges from 0.69 to 0.19.
 &lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;text-align:center&quot;&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;/dsablog/img/plot.png&quot; width=&quot;75% height= &quot;75%&quot; center&quot; style=&quot;padding:6px&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;em&gt;
 Figure 2. Scatter plots showing the performance of GLM on the test dataset for six randomly selected seeds. The red lines represent a 1:1 line between estimated and measured yields. Subfigures A–F refer to six plots prepared using six randomly generated numbers (seeds). performance. At a 99% confidence interval, the mean RMSE was 1.31–1.36 ton/ha on the test dataset (see table 1). 
 &lt;/em&gt; 
 &lt;br&gt;
 &lt;br&gt;
&lt;em&gt;
 Table 1. Table showing RMSE (ton/ha) values at 99% CI for training, CV, and test datasets for three hidden layers.
 &lt;/em&gt;
 &lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;text-align:center&quot;&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;/dsablog/img/table.PNG&quot; width=&quot;100% center&quot; style=&quot;padding:6px&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
 Overall, the GLM model employing the ten most influential parameters revealed the best prediction results. Thus, the developed method employs both the capability of the AutomL package as well as the capability of GLM to search for hyperparameters. In terms of performance, revealing higher wheat prediction capability, this combined approach seems synergetic and fast compared to the rest ones. 
&lt;br&gt;
 &lt;br&gt;
Moreover, as the study was implemented under a small dataset and because the AutoML offered the ten most influential parameters, this contributed to the obtained higher performance. From a practical perspective, this has invaluable significance. The efficient and effective training of machine learning models is often a very daunting task. Nonetheless, in this study, better results were obtained using an automated machine learning method that can be easily implemented by experts having limited skills. This implies the scalability of the approach to environments with limited access to well-skilled experts and robust off-the-shelf data mining platforms.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
 &lt;b&gt;Concluding Remarks&lt;/b&gt;
 &lt;br&gt;
 &lt;br&gt;
 A combined method, the AutoML with GLM hyperparameter tuning, showed higher performance over the rest of the methods. Millions of farmers across the African continent and beyond could take the advantage of the AutoML with GLM hyperparameter method to predict wheat yield. Moreover, it could be adapted to predict grain yields for other cereal. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
 &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.3390/agriculture12091352&quot;&gt;Full Article Link &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Andualem Aklilu</name></author><summary type="html">Why and How Satellite based Yield Prediction ? Smallholder farming is a predominant global agricultural system. In the developing world, it takes the lion share, for instance, in Ethiopia, it produced about 95% of main crops and cash crops. Despite its dominance, this farming practice, largely, is characterized by low crop productivity and absence of, and if there is any, the use of old-age unproductive technologies. Consequently, millions of societies around the globe are threatened by food insecurity. Countries like Ethiopia, for instance, imported 30% - 50% of their wheat demand annually. With the fast advancement of space technologies, remote sensing (RS)-based prediction methods are preferred over traditional tiresome and costly ground surveys. In harnessing the potential of remote sensing technologies, optical and radar sensors, in their order, probably are the two widely explored technologies. Existing prediction methods, which often operate at national and regional scales, exploit the potential of the well-established coarse spatial and temporal resolution sensors. Nonetheless, the resolution of these sensors has limited their application for field-scale prediction in smallholder systems. Data mining methods are also the key components of prediction methods. Despite statistical methods are widely being exploited the new era methods: machine learning and deep learning present superior potential. In this regard, this study was motivated to address some of challenges in yield prediction via setting threefold objective. First, the study aimed to evaluate the potential of selected vegetation indices derived from Sentinel-2 data that were representative of an optical sensor as wheat yield predictors. Second, it was set to evaluate the potential of selected SAR indices derived from Sentinel-1 data as wheat yield predictors. Third, we aimed to apply fast, reproducible, and open-source statistical, machine learning, and deep learning algorithms for wheat yield prediction. Key Findings This study aimed to develop a method for remote sensing-based wheat yield prediction. The study obtained predictors from vegetation indices derived from high-resolution optical and SAR sensors. Eight vegetation indices were computed from Sentinel-2 sensor, and five SAR indices were calculated from the Sentinel-1 sensor. In light of tapping the diverse potential, data mining methods, which are grouped under three broad categories: statistical, machine learning, and deep learning, were applied. The combined-date SAR indices, such as SAR Normalized Difference (SND) and SAR Simple Ratio (SSR) showed relatively improved performance over single date SAR indices. Indices such as SND and SSR achieved values of 1.32 ton/ha and 1.20 ton/ha, and values of 1.24 ton/ha and 1.22 ton/ha for LOORMSE (leave-one-out RMSE) and RMSE, respectively. It is intuitive to expect combined-date indices integrating wider phenological information to outperform narrow ones, single date. The most salient result of the current study is the successful application of an Automated Machine Learning platform, AutoML. The AutoML easily offers the 10 most powerful predictors (see figure 1) of the total 48 predictors considered. The 10 influential predictors are: 1. lai1020ha (leaf area index dated on October 20 per hectare) 2. ndwi1010ha (normalized difference water index dated on October 10 per hectare) 3. lai1010ha (leaf area index dated on October 10 per hectare) 4. ndwi1015ha (normalized difference water index dated on October 15 per hectare) 5. mcari1010ha (modified chlorophyll absorption ratio Index dated on October 10 per hectare) 6. fapar1010ha (fraction of absorbed photosynthetically active radiation index dated on October 10 per hectare) 7. ndwi1020ha (normalized difference water index dated on October 20 per hectare) 8. vh1015ha (single date synthetic aperture radar cross polarized index dated on October 15 per hectare) 9. ndi451010ha (normalized difference index using band 4 and 5 dated on October 10 per hectare), 10. fapar1005ha (fraction of absorbed photosynthetically active radiation index dated on October 05 per hectare) Figure 1. A plot showing the top ten most influential variables using the GLM model. Discriminating the ten parameters, a stand-alone algorithm: the GLM model, which happens the best of all the tested algorithms, revealed an RMSE of 0.84–0.98 ton/ha for the mean population at a 99% confidence interval (CI) on the test dataset, while the performance on the training dataset was 0.84–0.88 ton/ha. Of all the predictors evaluated, leaf area index calculated at the post-grain-filling stage is the most influential one (see figure 1 above). Validation of results also implemented to come up with conclusive outputs (see figure 2). On the test dataset, six scatter plots for six GLM models using different seeds were computed. Accordingly, the correlation coefficient (r) between the estimated and measured yield ranges from 0.69 to 0.19. Figure 2. Scatter plots showing the performance of GLM on the test dataset for six randomly selected seeds. The red lines represent a 1:1 line between estimated and measured yields. Subfigures A–F refer to six plots prepared using six randomly generated numbers (seeds). performance. At a 99% confidence interval, the mean RMSE was 1.31–1.36 ton/ha on the test dataset (see table 1). Table 1. Table showing RMSE (ton/ha) values at 99% CI for training, CV, and test datasets for three hidden layers. Overall, the GLM model employing the ten most influential parameters revealed the best prediction results. Thus, the developed method employs both the capability of the AutomL package as well as the capability of GLM to search for hyperparameters. In terms of performance, revealing higher wheat prediction capability, this combined approach seems synergetic and fast compared to the rest ones. Moreover, as the study was implemented under a small dataset and because the AutoML offered the ten most influential parameters, this contributed to the obtained higher performance. From a practical perspective, this has invaluable significance. The efficient and effective training of machine learning models is often a very daunting task. Nonetheless, in this study, better results were obtained using an automated machine learning method that can be easily implemented by experts having limited skills. This implies the scalability of the approach to environments with limited access to well-skilled experts and robust off-the-shelf data mining platforms. Concluding Remarks A combined method, the AutoML with GLM hyperparameter tuning, showed higher performance over the rest of the methods. Millions of farmers across the African continent and beyond could take the advantage of the AutoML with GLM hyperparameter method to predict wheat yield. Moreover, it could be adapted to predict grain yields for other cereal. Full Article Link</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">How Can We Translate Data Science into Policy?</title><link href="http://www.datascienceafrica.org/dsablog/2023/07/17/data-science-for-policy.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How Can We Translate Data Science into Policy?" /><published>2023-07-17T18:15:13+03:00</published><updated>2023-07-17T18:15:13+03:00</updated><id>http://www.datascienceafrica.org/dsablog/2023/07/17/data-science-for-policy</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://www.datascienceafrica.org/dsablog/2023/07/17/data-science-for-policy.html">&lt;p style=&quot;color:gray;&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Consulting researchers for evidence is not in the culture of African leaders but it is our role to make them appreciate this approach.” A participant at a Data Science Africa event - 2023 - in Kigali&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Data Science Africa (DSA) has built a strong foundation of data literacy through its various programs and training events and continues to nurture a community of African data scientists. At a recent event in Kigali, the community sought to take the impact of DSA to another level by exploring the potential of research and projects to support effective data-driven policy-making in Africa.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
I was interested in this, having experienced firsthand the need to link data science with decision-making while working as a data analyst at UN Global Pulse Kampala. Last year, I worked with DSA to curate a series of talks, one-on-one conversations, and open discussions, all of which proved very enlightening. The aim was to empower participants to think beyond developing data-centric solutions and consider how data science might affect policy-making.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;At the Kigali event, the highlight was an open discussion in which we examined challenges, explored our role as data scientists, and spotted opportunities for research on how data science can support policy.
 &lt;br&gt;
 &lt;br&gt;
In a room full of data-driven solution developers, with only a handful of decision-makers, participants had a lively discussion that showed diverse perspectives. Yet a notable consensus was evident – a shared recognition of the role data scientists can play. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--h4&gt;Where are these solutions located?&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;img class=&quot;&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;/dsablog/img/posts/map3.png&quot; align=&quot;left&quot; width=&quot;60%&quot; style=&quot;padding:6px&quot;&gt;
&lt;!-- &lt;span class=&quot;caption text-muted&quot;&gt;Figure 1: shows No of data-driven Covid-19 solutions collected by country (which is not a representation of all country solutions due to data collection limitations)&lt;/span&gt; --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Participants were asked what challenges they had experienced in translating data science solutions into pointers for practical policy. 
 &lt;br&gt;
 &lt;be&gt;
&lt;em&gt;“It’s challenging to explain the data science solutions to policymakers,”&lt;/em&gt; said one.
 &lt;br&gt;
 &lt;be&gt;
&lt;em&gt;“The needs of decision-makers are ever-changing, making it hard to find or generate relevant and timely evidence,”&lt;/em&gt; said another.
 &lt;br&gt;
 &lt;be&gt;
A third noted: &lt;em&gt;“There are many other things that influence policy, e.g., politics, which hinder data use.” &lt;/em&gt;
 &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; The discussion showed data scientists feel responsible for communicating their findings in ways that make sense to policymakers. 
 &lt;br&gt;
 &lt;be&gt;
&lt;em&gt;“We need to begin projects with an end in mind,” said one. “We are not doing data-driven projects for the sake of it but so that the solutions can be utilized.”&lt;/em&gt;
 &lt;br&gt;
 &lt;be&gt;
&lt;em&gt;“We need to produce impact-oriented research, which takes time and probably more resources but increases the chances of it being used to inform decision-making,”&lt;/em&gt; said another.
 &lt;br&gt;
 &lt;br&gt;
A number of speakers noted the need for data scientists to try to understand policymakers and engage in conversations that can influence policies. Some went as far as to suggest that data scientists should start looking at playing other roles, &lt;em&gt;“not just coding”&lt;/em&gt;, to increase the chances of influencing policy.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;be&gt;
 &lt;em&gt;“Consulting researchers for evidence is not in the culture of African leaders but it is our role to make them appreciate this approach,”&lt;/em&gt; said one bold thinker.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; As our keynote speaker, we were lucky to have Diasmer Bloe, a strategy and evaluation professional from Data for Policy, a global forum for knowledge-sharing and collaboration on evidence-based practices. (Diasmer is the researcher on the Africa Engagement Project, which aims to boost African academic, industry, and policy participation in  the Data for Policy community.)  
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
Diasmer enlightened us with valuable insights into data-driven policy-making and shed some light on how well it was going in Africa. She highlighted challenges in this area, which resonated with our concerns. For example, we learned that policymakers are increasingly interested in making use of data science but are still limited by their access to data, capacity to make sense of it, and financial resources. 
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
My own involvement in facilitating these sessions has taught me that both data scientists and policymakers must bridge the gap between scientific findings and policy decisions.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to Data for Policy, policymakers need to learn how to be both consumers and producers of evidence. This requires them to learn about different data sources and data-driven methods. From our side, we data scientists need a better understanding of policymakers’ challenges in order to raise their confidence in data-driven projects.  
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
Among prevailing issues, DSA recognizes the challenges with data discoverability, sharing, and interoperability; the limitations of human and technical capacities; and the legitimacy of public concerns. But the DSA community sees these challenges as opportunities, driving our work to strengthen policy with hard evidence.  
 &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; After the event, I was left pondering a question from the DSA chairperson, who asked: “Are there solid examples of use and impact that justify the need for data integration into policymaking?”
In other words, is data science credible? What do we need to do to raise public trust? And how can we create a data-driven culture in public institutions? For community members, these are potential research questions. 
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
Indeed, the journey ahead is exciting as we empower the community to innovate solutions and build policymakers’ trust. An interdisciplinary community with a shared interest in the potential and effect of data science on policy is only the first step. DSA wants members to explore more avenues and opportunities.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
We welcome your stories of successful data-centric solutions. If you would like to get in touch, you can contact DSA here: &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:info@datascienceafrica.org&quot;&gt;info@datascienceafrica.org&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Morine Amutorine</name></author><summary type="html">“Consulting researchers for evidence is not in the culture of African leaders but it is our role to make them appreciate this approach.” A participant at a Data Science Africa event - 2023 - in Kigali Data Science Africa (DSA) has built a strong foundation of data literacy through its various programs and training events and continues to nurture a community of African data scientists. At a recent event in Kigali, the community sought to take the impact of DSA to another level by exploring the potential of research and projects to support effective data-driven policy-making in Africa. I was interested in this, having experienced firsthand the need to link data science with decision-making while working as a data analyst at UN Global Pulse Kampala. Last year, I worked with DSA to curate a series of talks, one-on-one conversations, and open discussions, all of which proved very enlightening. The aim was to empower participants to think beyond developing data-centric solutions and consider how data science might affect policy-making.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">COVID-19 Misinformation Detection and Sentiment Analysis Models from Luganda</title><link href="http://www.datascienceafrica.org/dsablog/2022/04/06/COVID-19-Misinformation-Detection.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="COVID-19 Misinformation Detection and Sentiment Analysis Models from Luganda" /><published>2022-04-06T22:33:13+03:00</published><updated>2022-04-06T22:33:13+03:00</updated><id>http://www.datascienceafrica.org/dsablog/2022/04/06/COVID-19-Misinformation-Detection</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://www.datascienceafrica.org/dsablog/2022/04/06/COVID-19-Misinformation-Detection.html">&lt;p&gt;The growth in the use of smartphones in Uganda has facilitated the increase in Internet usage and internet subscribers in the country. The Internet has provided a fertile ground to generate huge amounts of information on various web and mobile based social media platforms. Social media platforms have overtaken traditional media in facilitating social interactions on real time events. The ever increasing number of social media users has resulted in an increase in social media content. This content has proven to be helpful for decision making.  However, since there are no restrictions and limitations on the content posted on social media platforms, it has turned out that some of the posted content is invalid, inaccurate, potentially and intentionally harmful. This poses a need to develop solutions that can be used to detect false information and misinformation in social media text. Several studies have sought and continue to detect negative and inaccurate content shared on social media platforms. However, most of this research has focused on the English language and thus these applications can not be used in contexts that include low resourced languages like Luganda, a major local language in Uganda that is also commonly used on social media platforms.
    &lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The focus of this research was on building a system for misinformation detection and sentiment analysis from social media text on Ugandan social media platforms. Our focus was mainly around social media content related to the current COVID-19 pandemic in Uganda. This was important to understand perceptions of Ugandas related to Uganda Government’s COVID-19 transmission mitigation strategies from social media data.  As a first step, we collected data related to COVID-19 from Facebook and Twitter using open source scraping tools. The data was analyzed and some of the key findings were that the text was in English, Luganda or a codemix of English and other local Ugandan languages like Luganda and Runyankole. For privacy reasons, the data was anonymized to remove any personal identification information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To prepare the dataset for machine learning tasks, the data was annotated using the open source Doccano annotation tool. Prior to the data annotation task, annotation guidelines were defined which guided the annotation activity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each social media datapoint was given the following labels: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Data Source: Facebook or Twitter &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Language: 
        &lt;ul&gt;
            &lt;li&gt;English- text data point is purely in English.&lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;li&gt;Luganda - text data point is purely in Luganda.&lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;li&gt;Codeswitched- text data point contains words in English and Luganda or in English and Runyankole.&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Misinformation: To model for misinformation analysis; four labels were used:
        &lt;ul&gt;
            &lt;li&gt;Fake - statement is misleading.&lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;li&gt;Not_Fake - statement is not misleading.&lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;li&gt;Partially Fake - part of the statement is misleading.&lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;li&gt;Others - scenarios where we couldn&apos;t prove whether the statement is false or not false.&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;  
    &lt;li&gt;Aspect: Topics on COVID-19 which included: COVID-19, Cases, Standard Operating Procedures (SOPs), Non-pharmaceutical Interventions (NPIs), Truck drivers, Hospitals, Vaccine, Elections, Treatment, Testing, COVID-19 Impact, Border, COVID-19 Relief, Presidential address, Death&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Sentiment: Tagged per Aspect with label of: Neutral, Positive and Negative. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


    &lt;div style=&quot;text-align:center&quot;&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;/dsablog/img/posts/covid-19.png&quot; width=&quot;100% center&quot; style=&quot;padding:6px&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;The figure above, shows an annotation of social media data in &lt;strong&gt;Luganda&lt;/strong&gt;  with the misinformation tagged as &lt;strong&gt;Not_Fake&lt;/strong&gt; and the aspect identified being &lt;strong&gt;Vaccine&lt;/strong&gt; with a &lt;strong&gt;Neutral&lt;/strong&gt; sentiment. &lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;After data annotation, we carried out an exploratory data analysis of the annotated data set that consisted of 11,000 text data points.The data obtained from Twitter contributed the highest percentage 51.4% compared to Facebook data with 48.6%. 93% of the annotated data points were in English while Luganda and Codemixed data points formed 5% and 1% respectively.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;div style=&quot;text-align:center&quot;&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;/dsablog/img/posts/source-of-covid.png&quot; width=&quot;50% center&quot; style=&quot;padding:6px&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

    &lt;div style=&quot;text-align:center&quot;&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;/dsablog/img/posts/language-distribution.png&quot; width=&quot;60% center&quot; style=&quot;padding:6px&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;To gain more insights from the data, we drafted research questions to guide the data analysis.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Question 1: What is the spread of misinformation in the data obtained from Twitter compared to the data obtained from Facebook?&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;To answer this question, we considered the misinformation label in the data.  Much as Twitter data was more than the Facebook data in terms of quantity, most of the data tagged with the &lt;strong&gt;&apos;Fake&apos;&lt;/strong&gt;, and &lt;strong&gt;&apos;Partially Fake&apos;&lt;/strong&gt; labels was the Facebook data. This can be attributed to the data that we obtained from Facebook that allowed us to include people’s comments to the Facebook posts compared to the Twitter data where we were restricted to only the posts made by the accounts scrapped. Moreover, Twitter has a limited tweet length of 280 characters compared to Facebook which means that while people make posts on Facebook, they are at liberty to write more which can turn out to be a source of misinformation. The demographic of Twitter and Facebook users is highly varied with more elites and corporate individuals on Twitter compared to Facebook. Corporates are more conscious about what they post and double check their posts or tweets.&lt;/p&gt;


    &lt;div style=&quot;text-align:center&quot;&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;/dsablog/img/posts/misinformation-review-by-source.png&quot; width=&quot;60% center&quot; style=&quot;padding:6px&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Question 2: What is the spread of misinformation in the English social media data compared to Luganda or code switched data?&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    
    &lt;p&gt;A categorization based on language was made to compare the levels of misinformation associated with a particular language. &lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;From this analysis, it was observed that most of the &apos;Fake&apos; and &apos;Not Fake&apos; posts were written in &lt;strong&gt;English&lt;/strong&gt; while most of the posts in  &lt;strong&gt;Luganda&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;codemixed&lt;/strong&gt; were tagged as &apos;Not_Fake&apos; or &apos;Others&apos;.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;div style=&quot;text-align:center&quot;&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;/dsablog/img/posts/misinformation-review-by-language.png&quot; width=&quot;60% center&quot; style=&quot;padding:6px&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


    &lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Question 3: What is the spread of misinformation in the social media data obtained in 2020 compared to data obtained in 2021?&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


    &lt;p&gt;Generally, we observe that we had more posts with the misinformation labels:  &lt;strong&gt;&apos;Fake&apos;&lt;/strong&gt;, and &lt;strong&gt;&apos;Partially Fake&apos;&lt;/strong&gt; in 2021 compared to 2020. &lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;div style=&quot;text-align:center&quot;&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;/dsablog/img/posts/misinformation-review-by-year.png&quot; width=&quot;60% center&quot; style=&quot;padding:6px&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;We also analyzed the misinformation data for 2021. From the data analysis, we observe that we had more posts labeled with misinformation in June and July 2021 compared to other months in the year. In June 2021, Uganda experienced its highest number of COVID-19 cases and deaths. This was attributed to the emergence of the Delta variant in the country.  Furthermore, all institutions of higher learning were closed  in June and a 42 days lockdown was announced for the transport and business sector. The lockdown was then lifted towards the end of July, however, schools remained closed. Considering all the events that were going on in the country at that time, we observed that there were many posts made on social media platforms and part of the data had misinformation labels.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Sample data points for that period:&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;A: “Covid19 is now a fertile business in Uganda, continue getting the money you in government”. &lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


    &lt;p&gt;We observe that this post has misinformation on COVID-19. Our model was able to classify this post as “Fake” with a Negative sentiment. &lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;B: “Okunoonyereza okukoleddwa ekitongole kulaze nti obwelaliikirivu bweyongedde mu bannayuganda olwembeera yekirwadde kya Covid-19 ekiyinza okwongera embeera yokwennyika ssinakindi endwadde zemitwe mu ggwanga”.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;We observe that the post was about a research conducted on the impact of COVID-19. Our model was able to classify this post as “Not_Fake” with a Negative sentiment.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Question 4: What is the correlation between the sentiments across different aspects in the social media dataset  ?&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;During the COVID-19 pandemic, a number of topics drove conversations on social media platforms. These aspects ranged from the COVID-19 symptoms, COVID-19 restrictions by the government and their effects. The posts and tweets made about COVID-19, Non Pharmaceutical Interventions (NPIs) which included closure of schools, businesses and curfew, and COVID-19 cases had more negative sentiments. All these aspects had a negative impact on the people which justifies the results obtained. For example, some were about closure of people’s business, deaths of loved ones and family members.  Additionally aspects like COVID relief and treatment had positive sentiment this can be attributed to the food and cash relief issued by the government and the many recoveries witnessed from the COVID-19 patients.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;div style=&quot;text-align:center&quot;&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;/dsablog/img/posts/distribution-of-sentiments-per-aspect.png&quot; width=&quot;60% center&quot; style=&quot;padding:6px&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


    &lt;p&gt;In conclusion, we see the potential in analyzing social media data to understand people’s sentiments to COVID-19 and its mitigation strategies in the country. We also observe that there is potential for the use of social media data for the spread of misinformation and the need to build misinformation classification models based on machine learning. &lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Dr Joyce Nakatumba Nabende</name></author><summary type="html">The growth in the use of smartphones in Uganda has facilitated the increase in Internet usage and internet subscribers in the country. The Internet has provided a fertile ground to generate huge amounts of information on various web and mobile based social media platforms. Social media platforms have overtaken traditional media in facilitating social interactions on real time events. The ever increasing number of social media users has resulted in an increase in social media content. This content has proven to be helpful for decision making. However, since there are no restrictions and limitations on the content posted on social media platforms, it has turned out that some of the posted content is invalid, inaccurate, potentially and intentionally harmful. This poses a need to develop solutions that can be used to detect false information and misinformation in social media text. Several studies have sought and continue to detect negative and inaccurate content shared on social media platforms. However, most of this research has focused on the English language and thus these applications can not be used in contexts that include low resourced languages like Luganda, a major local language in Uganda that is also commonly used on social media platforms.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Deploying data in Covid-19 response - What worked?</title><link href="http://www.datascienceafrica.org/dsablog/2021/12/14/what-worked.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Deploying data in Covid-19 response - What worked?" /><published>2021-12-14T22:33:13+03:00</published><updated>2021-12-14T22:33:13+03:00</updated><id>http://www.datascienceafrica.org/dsablog/2021/12/14/what-worked</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://www.datascienceafrica.org/dsablog/2021/12/14/what-worked.html">&lt;p&gt;“Covid-19 has been a catalyst to data innovation” is a phrase that has been thrown around very often by many (I know I have); but how far do real-world experiences support this statement? 
    &lt;br&gt;Covid-19 intensified the urgent need for timely data and information for decision making, with data playing an important role in policies relating to disease surveillance, health and relief resources allocation and prioritization, cases and mortality prediction, amongst other areas. Drawing from real-world examples of the use of data science in the Covid-19 response, in this article, I review the strategies that made data use for Covid-19 a lot more possible than we have seen before. 
    &lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;div style=&quot;text-align:center&quot;&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;/dsablog/img/posts/what_worked/institutions.png&quot; width=&quot;25% center&quot; style=&quot;padding:6px&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;h4&gt;Institutions were poised to act and to work together.&lt;/h4&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;The urgency of the pandemic meant organizations of all types were poised to take on new roles and work in new ways, creating a demand for data-enabled innovations. There was a clear and immediate need for reliable and timely data. 
            Organizations like the Global Partnership for Sustainable Development Data &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.data4sdgs.org/news/covid-19-data-resilient-africa&quot; target=&quot;blank&quot;&gt;(GPSDD) played a huge role&lt;/a&gt; in initiating and establishing grounds for data partnerships and were a catalyst for many governments aided data-driven solutions. GPSDD approached several national statistical offices in Africa and convened various actors (from policy, data providers, analysts and others), to help get new projects  off the ground. Working across organisations in this way helped identify data needs and challenges that different national statistical offices were facing, exploring data access possibilities and bringing other partners on board for the analysis to happen. As a result, new coalitions were mobilized to help in identifying what data was available, what was missing, and who could fill the gaps. New partnerships were set up with relevant institutions, e.g. Centre for Disease Controls (CDC), to request access to data. The willingness with which national statistical offices and partners engaged with organizations like GPSDD to explore and uncover their data needs and challenges resulted in the analysis being possible faster than it would have been in a different case.
            &lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Other factors that made these collaborations and solutions successful included mechanisms for sharing data routinely rather than once, data harmonization, and the subsidized or no cost for Covid-19 dashboards (zero-rating data dashboards that can receive data from users).  
            Case studies show that collaborations were more straightforward and faster where there were pre-existing relationships on the country level. Having already established engagements between various actors like local authorities, NGOs and other solution providers served as a good foundation for the analysis to occur quickly. 
            &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;div style=&quot;text-align:center&quot;&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;/dsablog/img/posts/what_worked/data-formats.png&quot; width=&quot;25%&quot; style=&quot;padding:6px&quot;&gt; &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;h4&gt;Data science solution providers devised alternative ways to obtain hard to get data that was in any way programmable.&lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Access to data has been a challenge, especially in the early stages of the pandemic. In many cases, absence of Covid-19 health data and data incompleteness made data analytics hard. Nevertheless, data scientists devised ways to gather supplementary data, for example, through weekly social media surveys distributed for people to share information about their symptoms, whether they had taken a Covid-19 test or not, and the test results. In another case, it became popular that health ministries in many countries shared Covid-19 status reports on their websites and/or social media pages for the public in pdfs and static images. With these, data scientists could conduct the extra work of turning this data into analyzable formats. With such alternative approaches, data analytics was made possible. &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The reality is that most data is not curated and organized in ways that make it accessible or usable to decision-makers and other policy stakeholders. Practitioners in private and public sectors are not collecting and managing data with awareness and plan for broader retrieval or analysis beyond the initially intended task. For Covid-19 response, data scientists worked out ways around these issues to make evidence-based predictions, prioritization and overall decision making possible for the pandemic response.&lt;/p&gt;
    
    &lt;div style=&quot;text-align:center&quot;&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;/dsablog/img/posts/what_worked/teams.png&quot; width=&quot;25%&quot; style=&quot;padding:6px&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
   &lt;h4&gt;Teams were ready to work in real-time.&lt;/h4&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;The Covid-19 emergency, like any emergency response, required swift actions that could not wait to follow the standard data science project life-cycle. Responders needed insights quickly, and everyone was under pressure to deliver, especially decision-makers. As a result, responders sought interventions that could be rapidly implemented without compromising on the status of the data analytics. In this case, teams had to do the “intensive human tasks” (for example, manually making sure data is relevant and accurate instead of creating and training models that might require more data and time) to ensure getting results in real-time.&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;In addition, teams quickly adapted to different reporting structures as long as they were accessible to decision-makers. 
                In some cases, insights never made it to fancy dashboards, but they reached decision-makers quickly. In other cases, already 
                existing platforms were repurposed to fit Covid-19 needs. A few examples here are platforms like &lt;a href=&quot;https://dhis2.org/category/covid-success-stories/&quot; target=&quot;blank&quot;&gt; DHIS2&lt;/a&gt; that developed 
                ready-to-install digital data packages to support Covid-19 surveillance &amp; response based on WHO guidelines. 
                Another example is &lt;a href=&quot;https://kenyacovid19.ushahidi.io/views/map&quot; target=&quot;blank&quot;&gt; Ushahidi&lt;/a&gt;, which developed a dashboard component tracking cases of Covid-19 and other resources, supplies and services, and news. Ushahidi also set up internet hotspots to host information centres that helped disseminate educational and health information (videos, pdfs and audios) to help people navigate challenges caused by the pandemic.
                &lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Data collected by private practitioners for their day to day operations played a vital role in enabling analytics that accessed 
                the social and economic impact of Covid-19. For example, mobile phone data for mobility tracking was widely reused with examples in 
                &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.flowminder.org/resources/publications/analysis-of-call-detail-records-to-inform-the-covid-19-response-in-ghana-opportunities-and-challenges&quot; target=&quot;blank&quot;&gt; Ghana&lt;/a&gt;, 
                &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.flowminder.org/resources/publications/covid-19-supporting-the-government-of-sierra-leone-with-mobility-data&quot; target=&quot;blank&quot;&gt; Sierra Leone&lt;/a&gt;, 
                &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.flowminder.org/resources/publications/covid-19-democratic-republic-of-the-congo-drc-report-may-2020-initial-insights-into-the-effect-of-mobility-restrictions-using-anonymised-and-aggregated-mobile-phone-data&quot; target=&quot;blank&quot;&gt;DRC&lt;/a&gt;, 
                &lt;a href=&quot;https://blogs.worldbank.org/developmenttalk/using-agent-based-modeling-and-telecom-data-inform-covid-19-response&quot; target=&quot;blank&quot;&gt;Gambia&lt;/a&gt;, 
                    and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.flowminder.org/resources/publications/covid-19-supporting-the-government-of-namibia-with-mobility-data&quot; target=&quot;blank&quot; &gt;Namibia&lt;/a&gt;.
                    Another example of private sector data reuse was &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.yoco.com/za/blog/covid-19-recovery-monitor/&quot; target=&quot;blank&quot;&gt;Yoco Financial data&lt;/a&gt; that the company repurposed to assess the effect of Covid-19 on small businesses turnover. &lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;These examples have illustrated that what is needed in a time of crisis is not only new technologies and platforms but already working solutions and leveraging existing links (collaborations). An additional key to this success was the speed of executions anticipating and dealing with changing needs as stakeholders got on board with data-driven solutions.&lt;/p&gt;

        &lt;div style=&quot;text-align:center&quot;&gt; &lt;img class=&quot;&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;/dsablog/img/posts/what_worked/agenda.png&quot; width=&quot;25%&quot; style=&quot;padding:6px&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;h4&gt;The agenda on data use was a priority for everyone.&lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.un.org/sites/un2.un.org/files/joint_statement_on_data_protection_and_privacy_in_covid-19_response.pdf&quot;&gt;joint UN statement&lt;/a&gt; on data protection and privacy in the Covid-19 response statement states that the collection, use, sharing and further processing of data can help limit the spread of the virus and aid in accelerating the recovery, primarily through digital contact tracing. 
        There has been evidence of an increased enthusiasm with which people tried to mobilize around new data sources or accessing existing information which has portrayed the level of value attached to the use of data for crisis response. One way that the agenda on data was pushed was by forming national Covid-19 task forces on data which mobilized relevant stakeholders and national leaders to unfasten critical roadblocks to data sharing and access to coordinate and advance the crisis response. The galvanized interest around data also made several analyses possible faster than it would have been in a different case.
        &lt;/p&gt;
        
        &lt;div style=&quot;text-align:center&quot;&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;/dsablog/img/posts/what_worked/what_worked01.png&quot; width=&quot;70%&quot; style=&quot;padding:6px&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All the above worked even though in Africa, we are faced with a data ecosystem that is still maturing, and that hasn’t yet worked through a lot of the issues around data governance and use. These include: how to navigate the vast regulatory burden that makes the subject of data access and sharing sensitive, how to operate within unclear legal frameworks (what should be public and not, which leaves solutions hidden from people that would benefit from them) and how to ensure data is privacy-safe but still useful for the analysis. &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To address these issues there is a need for various interventions, including; building capacity to develop data-enabled solutions and to address data needs, addressing the gaps in data sharing laws, mechanisms and policies, and creating institutional and technology infrastructures to unlock access and enable effective data sharing and policies across public institutions. While there is noticeable progress caused by the united stand that has been towards responding to Covid-19, there remains work to do if Africa is to harness the benefits of data in policy responses.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So, it’s true, the novelty and urgency of the pandemic brought about openness and a learning appetite (about new approaches, interest in the 
        new ways of doing things which fostered data innovations), and there is a lot that we can learn from the various
         &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.datascienceafrica.org/dsablog/2021/08/26/data-driven-covid-19-solutions-in-africa.html&quot; target=&quot;blank&quot;&gt;examples done across 
        Africa&lt;/a&gt; to improve data innovation for social good, beyond Covid-19. &lt;/p&gt;    
    &lt;p&gt;However, if we are truly going to say that covid-19 has been a catalyst for data-enabled innovation, we need to ask:
        How do these lessons tie into the policy requirements of data access and use? This is the next question we are answering through &lt;a href=&quot;https://mamutorine.github.io/about/&quot; target=&quot;blank&quot;&gt;this project&lt;/a&gt;. 
        &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The findings in this article are a result of a conversation from real-world experiences shared during the “Data sharing for Covid-19 response: 
    lessons from African experiences for the development of data policy” (20th October 2021) focus workshop convened under the 
    &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.datascienceafrica.org/dsa-visiting-fellowship/&quot; target=&quot;blank&quot;&gt;DSA visiting fellowship program&lt;/a&gt;, 
    to support the project &lt;a href=&quot;https://mamutorine.github.io/about/&quot; target=&quot;blank&quot;&gt;“Increasing Data Sharing from Africa’s Covid-19 Response”&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;em&gt;Great thanks go to everyone who participated in the workshop and the Data Science Africa team for the support and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.csap.cam.ac.uk/network/jessica-montgomery/&quot;&gt;Jessica Montgomery&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://inverseprobability.com/&quot;&gt;Prof. Neil Lawrence&lt;/a&gt; for the overall guidance on this project.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;em&gt; Reach out to: &lt;a href =&quot;mailto:amutorine@gmail.com&quot; target=&quot;blank&quot;&gt;Morine Amutorine&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;!-- &lt;h4&gt;Where are these solutions located?&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;img class=&quot;&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;/dsablog/img/posts/map3.png&quot; align=&quot;left&quot; width=&quot;60%&quot; style=&quot;padding:6px&quot;&gt; --&gt;
&lt;!-- &lt;span class=&quot;caption text-muted&quot;&gt;Figure 1: shows No of data driven Covid-19 solutions collected by country, (which is not a representation of all country solutions due to data collection limitations)&lt;/span&gt; --&gt;

&lt;!-- &lt;p&gt;In April (2021), we set out to collect data about data driven Covid-19 solutions in Africa, with the aim of analysing various characteristics of the projects and  developing a data sharing framework for social good beyond Covid-19 in the African context. We wanted to explore the datasets and data access strategies used, the skills and expertise needed for effective collaborations, technical requirements, and barriers to effective data sharing. Our objective for this review was to learn more about the challenges and opportunities encountered on various projects. We hope to establish where projects face common challenges, where there is consensus about the need for policy intervention, and what type of policy intervention could help. &lt;/p&gt; --&gt;


&lt;!-- &lt;p&gt;To date, we have collected about 65 data driven Covid-19 solutions and initiatives in Africa from both &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/forms/d/e/1FAIpQLSdLSRSxjIVZeXqVLcWbtv1t_IqzXP6gXbhFCIfzeIulDY6DhA/viewform&quot;&gt;the survey&lt;/a&gt; and targeted online search. This write up is an overview of our findings and a summary of the ongoing and future work towards developing a data sharing framework and contributing to &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.datascienceafrica.org/dsa-visiting-fellowship/&quot;&gt;Data Science Africa’s efforts to support data policies&lt;/a&gt; in Africa.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt; --&gt;</content><author><name>Morine Amutorine</name></author><summary type="html">“Covid-19 has been a catalyst to data innovation” is a phrase that has been thrown around very often by many (I know I have); but how far do real-world experiences support this statement? Covid-19 intensified the urgent need for timely data and information for decision making, with data playing an important role in policies relating to disease surveillance, health and relief resources allocation and prioritization, cases and mortality prediction, amongst other areas. Drawing from real-world examples of the use of data science in the Covid-19 response, in this article, I review the strategies that made data use for Covid-19 a lot more possible than we have seen before.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Increasing Data Sharing from Africa’s Covid-19 Response</title><link href="http://www.datascienceafrica.org/dsablog/2021/08/26/data-driven-covid-19-solutions-in-africa.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Increasing Data Sharing from Africa’s Covid-19 Response" /><published>2021-08-26T17:45:13+03:00</published><updated>2021-08-26T17:45:13+03:00</updated><id>http://www.datascienceafrica.org/dsablog/2021/08/26/data-driven-covid-19-solutions-in-africa</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://www.datascienceafrica.org/dsablog/2021/08/26/data-driven-covid-19-solutions-in-africa.html">&lt;p&gt;Data science communities across Africa have created - and are still developing - innovative uses of data and statistics to support Covid-19 response teams in mitigating the Covid-19 pandemic. These solutions aim to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Increase the effectiveness &lt;b&gt;of emergency response&lt;/b&gt; (like monitoring the extent of the disease spread among populations);&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Improve surveillance&lt;/b&gt; (by estimating the prevalence of Covid-19 and understanding the symptoms); and &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Aid decision making&lt;/b&gt; (by investigating how different policy interventions have affected businesses, livelihoods, and economies).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;



&lt;p&gt;By reviewing the landscape of data science-enabled Covid-19 response projects in Africa, this project aims to identify policy interventions that can enable more effective data sharing in future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Where are these solutions located?&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;img class=&quot;&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;/dsablog/img/posts/map3.png&quot; align=&quot;left&quot; width=&quot;60%&quot; style=&quot;padding:6px&quot;&gt;
&lt;!-- &lt;span class=&quot;caption text-muted&quot;&gt;Figure 1: shows No of data driven Covid-19 solutions collected by country, (which is not a representation of all country solutions due to data collection limitations)&lt;/span&gt; --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In April (2021), we set out to collect data about data driven Covid-19 solutions in Africa, with the aim of analysing various characteristics of the projects and  developing a data sharing framework for social good beyond Covid-19 in the African context. We wanted to explore the datasets and data access strategies used, the skills and expertise needed for effective collaborations, technical requirements, and barriers to effective data sharing. Our objective for this review was to learn more about the challenges and opportunities encountered on various projects. We hope to establish where projects face common challenges, where there is consensus about the need for policy intervention, and what type of policy intervention could help. &lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;To date, we have collected about 65 data driven Covid-19 solutions and initiatives in Africa from both &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/forms/d/e/1FAIpQLSdLSRSxjIVZeXqVLcWbtv1t_IqzXP6gXbhFCIfzeIulDY6DhA/viewform&quot;&gt;the survey&lt;/a&gt; and targeted online search. This write up is an overview of our findings and a summary of the ongoing and future work towards developing a data sharing framework and contributing to &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.datascienceafrica.org/dsa-visiting-fellowship/&quot;&gt;Data Science Africa’s efforts to support data policies&lt;/a&gt; in Africa.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;!-- &lt;h4&gt;What do we know so far?&lt;/h4&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Data driven Covid-19 solutions analysed so far cut across a variety of data types and other general initiatives as shown in the following figures.&lt;/p&gt; --&gt;
&lt;img class=&quot;img-fluid&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;/dsablog/img/posts/datas2t.png&quot;&gt;
&lt;!--     &lt;center&gt;
       &lt;img class=&quot;img-fluid&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;/dsablog/img/posts/bars.png&quot;&gt;

        &lt;img style=&quot;height: 500px;&quot;  class=&quot;img-fluid&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;/dsablog/img/posts/circles.png&quot;&gt;
   
   &lt;/center&gt;      --&gt;
&lt;!-- &lt;span class=&quot;caption text-muted&quot;&gt;Figure 2: shows a Summary of data types used (as of the data collected)&lt;/span&gt; --&gt;



&lt;p&gt;We have tried to explore the status (i.e., level of solution uptake in the real world) of the projects in our database by categorizing them as; pilot not ready to deploy, pilot ready to deploy and in use. This kind of analysis will help us draw some insights into solution uptake and what roles various factors like data used, nature of collaborations, stakeholders involved and more, play in solution uptake.  Extracting any patterns in projects that get used and those that stay at pilot level (or research level) can provide insights that can help inform future approaches to projects, to increase their chances of being adopted in the real world. &lt;/p&gt;



&lt;h4&gt;What’s in progress?&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are currently conducting a case-by-case analysis of the Covid-19 solutions to establish the Africa situation in regards to data sharing for social good and also identify focal points for targeted engagements.  Survey responses so far have highlighted the following key areas for action:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Data:&lt;/b&gt; A variety of different data types can be used in Covid-19 response, and different data types will pose different analytical challenges. Data scientists are grappling with issues of accessibility and usability, with different levels of data quality or data formats, and with questions about storage and sharing formats, and replicable frameworks available to process and analyze various data types&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Collaborations:&lt;/b&gt; For an application to work well once deployed, it must be designed with user needs in mind. Survey respondents have been grappling with understanding which stakeholders have what requirements, and how best to engage with different potential user groups, defining the roles that different actors play across a project’s life, uptake, and impact. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Skills:&lt;/b&gt; Effective deployment of data science applications requires teams with diverse skillsets that can engage different stakeholders. Further work is now needed to understand what capabilities are needed in a data science team, and how to access this multidisciplinary expertise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Data stewardship:&lt;/b&gt; In addition to issues of data access, a variety of data stewardship issues must be addressed to ensure trustworthy use of data. This project will seek to understand the challenges that arise across the data pipeline from creation, ownership, accessibility, and sharing for data analysis and use. This includes consideration of topics such as privacy, security, and the cultural norms that govern these practices and come up with checklist toolkits to aid future work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Policy:&lt;/b&gt; Drawing from these experiences, this project will seek to establish how the challenges tie into the policy requirements of data access and use, and propose guidelines for handling requirements, barriers, opportunities, gaps, risks, and approaches to data sharing.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h4&gt;What questions about Africa’s Covid-19 response, need answering to increase data sharing for social good beyond Covid-19?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;What data access strategies have been successful during and can be adopted from the Covid-19 response? How could these be adopted in the longer-term?&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
    What intervention processes and procedures have proved productive in forming data collaborations for Covid-19 response? 
    How have projects brought users or other stakeholders into project development?
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;What roles do skills and expertise play in building effective data collaborations?&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;What issues of data governance and data stewardship were encountered during the Covid-19 response? What privacy obligations, technical requirements and social and cultural barriers affect data sharing? &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;How can we build capabilities in the long-term?&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;What policy interventions would help address or lessen the impact of the current barriers to the use of data science in policy?&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Why are some solutions more widespread and others not?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The study of the above mentioned factors (data, collaborations, skills, stewardship and policies) plus answering these questions will help us develop an operational context that fosters data sharing, and derive guidelines on &lt;b&gt;best practices&lt;/b&gt; that can be adapted and replicated, &lt;b&gt;lessons&lt;/b&gt; from what did not work and &lt;b&gt;recommendations&lt;/b&gt; from what has worked in the Covid-19 response. We will then map out practical actions that can create data ecosystems that foster data sharing, increasing the use of data for innovation and social good. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://mamutorine.github.io/about/&quot;&gt;Project Background&lt;/a&gt;  | &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.datascienceafrica.org/dsa-visiting-fellowship/&quot;&gt;About Data Science Africa Visiting Fellowship &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;em&gt; Reach out to: &lt;a href =&quot;mailto:amutorine@gmail.com&quot; target=&quot;blank&quot;&gt;Morine Amutorine&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption text-muted&quot;&gt;Acknowledgements for data collection go to: &lt;b&gt;Wuraola Oyewusi, Ayomide Owoyemi, Ernest Mwebaze, Jessica Oyugi, Aurelle Tchagna Kouanou, Tamaro Green, Ezekiel Adebayo Ogundepo and Vasileios Lampos.&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Morine Amutorine &amp; Jessica Montgomery</name></author><summary type="html">Data science communities across Africa have created - and are still developing - innovative uses of data and statistics to support Covid-19 response teams in mitigating the Covid-19 pandemic. These solutions aim to:</summary></entry></feed>